A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, Special Events and Activities, Botany Exhibit FA882
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, Special Events and Activities, Botany Exhibit
1967
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Rockefeller University
FA882
0.88 Cubic Feet 2 boxes
2 boxes.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 600-11
Biographical / Historical
In 1967 McGraw Hill published for the New York Botanical Garden, Harold W. Rickett's WILD FLOWERS OF THE UNITED STATES. Celebrating this publication The Rockefeller University arranged an exhibit entitled "Three Centuries of Botany in North America." The publication of Harold Rickett's volume 1 was made possible by the National Committee for the Wild Flowers of the United States under the leadership of Mrs. David Rockefeller and Mr. Diarmuid C. Russell. The publication was dedicated to David and Peggy Rockefeller.
The Exhibit was open March 22-April 14, 1967 in The Abby Aldrich Building on The Rockefeller University campus. Rare books were loaned by The New York Public Library, The New York Botanical Garden, The American Philosophical Society, The Library Company of Philadelphia, The Royal Botanic Gardens, The William L. Clements Library, The New York Academy of Medicine, The New Church Library, Stechert-Hafner, Inc.
Custodial History
Received or inventoried, April 1979.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for scholarly research.
Scope and Contents
Exhibit books and transparencies.
A record of the exhibit was made in black and white photographs. They are for identification only and are not intended to be of reproductive quality (negatives are part of the record). A number of color transparencies of unusual quality were made and prints were used for exhibition purposes. The master transparency is filed with the loose-leaf pages of the exhibit record, but additional copies were made and form part of this collection.
Genetics; Biology -- Research; Medical care; DNA; China; Cell and biomolecular sciences; Vivisection; Medical research; Medical sciences; Medicine, Preventive; McCarty, Maclyn; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Avery, Oswald Theodore; Seitz, Frederick; Rockefeller University; MacLeod, Colin M. (Colin Munro)
- Botany Exhibit, 1967
  - Catalog describing the exhibit (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - The Rockefeller University Review, 1967 March-April
      Scope and Contents note
      p. 1-10 article by Sir George Taylor
    - Photographs at opening of exhibition (some identifications).
  - Letter of transmittal and working papers (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Color transparencies
    Contents list indicates where master transparency is filed with the loose-leaf pages of the exhibit record.
    - #8 Catesby, Mark. "Natural History of North Carolina" color plate facing p. 82 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - #8 Catesby, Mark. "Natural History of North Carolina" Plate facing 120: Bison (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - #22 Taylor, Simon, "Drawings of North American Plants"
      - Matricaria Pl. 116 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Oenothera Pl. 492 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Polygonum Pl. 516 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Scrophularia Pl. 863 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Coreopsis Pl. 1283 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Parthenium Pl. 1402 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - #31 Bartram, William
      - Pl. XI (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Pl. XIV Morning glory (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - p. 106 Frankinia (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Duplicate set of prints (incomplete) black and white (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Negatives for black and white exhibit photos (Box 1, Folder 14)
    See contents list # 1-8, 9-45, 46-65.
    Negatives identified but not listed in contents list.
  - Loose-leaf exhibit pages
    Arrangement note
    Numbered according to contents list numbers and arranged following the Exhibit Catalog's description of each book described.
    - #1-10 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - #11-23 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - #24-35 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - #36-47 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - # 48-65 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Copy of Contents list (Box 2)
  - Content list
    - 1. A briefe and true report of the new found land of Virginia. By Thomas Hariot
      Loaned by The New York Public Library.
      Title page A2 spread.
      Set of negatives in Box 1.
    - 2. Canadensium Plantarum. By Jacques Philippe Cornuti
      Loaned by New York Botanical Garden.
      Title page.
      Aguilegia pumila praecox canad, p. 60.
      Edera Trifolia Canadensus (poison ivy) p. 97.
    - 3. Theatrum Botanicum. By John Parkinson
      Title.
      Frontispiece.
      Text with three woodblocks, p. 857.
    - 4. Musaeum Tradescantianum. By John Tradescant
      Title page spread, two pages Engraving of Tradescant, the Elder.
      Engraving of Tradescant, the Younger.
      Text pages: 73, 74.
      Set of negative in Box 1.
    - 5. New Englands rarities discovered. By John Josselyn
      Loaned by Library Company of Philadelphia.
      Purpurea, pitcher plant, p. 54.
      The small sunflower, p. 02.
      Snake Head, Cholone Glabra, p. 78.
      No negatives found.
    - 6. Catalogue of plants of Virginia. By John Banister
      Title page of John Ray's Historiae Plantarum v. 2, 1693 1927, 1928 (1), 1928 (2).
    - 7. Phytographia. By Leonard Plukenet
      Plate cciii.
      Notes by Lambert "Lab 203".
    - 8. The natural history of Carolina. By Mark Catesby
      Loaned by the; Hew York Botanical Garden and American Philosophical Society.
      1st edition, 1731 Title page, p. 48 and Plate facing 48, p. 61 and plate facing 61.
      2nd edition, 1771 Title page, Plate facing page 82 (color transparency), page 120, Plate facing page 120 (color transparency).
      Set of negatives in Box 1 but labeling on negatives as well as prints is confused.
    - 9. Hortus Britanno-Americanus
      Issued as a "new" work in London 1763 using Catesby's plates and text.
      Negative in Box 1, but print is lacking.
    - 10. Hortus Europae Americanus
      Issued London 1767: a new title page for the above item.
      Negative in Box 1.
    - 11. Classes Plantarum. By Carl Linnaeus
      Loaned by Stechert-Hafner.
      No negative found.
    - 12. Flora Virginica. By J.F. Gronovius and John Clayton
    - 13. Impregnation of the seeds of plants. By James Logan
      Loaned, by the American Philosophical Society.
      p. 192 facsimile.
      Negative of page 191. in Box 1.
    - 14. Experimenta et Meletemata de plantarum generatione. By James Logan
      Loaned by The American Philosophical Society.
      page 3 facsimile.
    - 15. A description of the English Province of Carolina. By Daniel Coxe
    - 16. Plantae Coldenghamiae. By Cadwallader Colden
      First title page, pt. one, 1742.
      Second title page, p. 47.
      Negatives in Box 1.
    - 17. Botanic manuscript of Jane Golden. By Jane Golden
      Facsimile published by The Garden Club of Orange and Dutchess Counties 1963.
      Page 86, 87.
    - 18. Observations... in his travels from Pensilvania. By John Bartram
      Loaned by Mew York Botanical Garden and American Philosophical Society.
      Preface.
      Observations...
    - 19. Catalogue d'arbustes and de plantes. By John Bartram
      Loaned by Now York Botanical Garden and American Philosophical Society.
      Broadside.
    - 20. En resa til Norra America. By Peter Kalm
      Loaned by Mow York Botanical Garden.
    - 21. Travels into North America. By Peter Kalm
      pp. 126, 127.
      Mo negatives found.
    - 22. Drawings of American plants. By Samuel Taylor
      Loaned by the Royal Botanical Gardens.
      Matricaria, plate 116.
      Oenothera, plate 492.
      Polygonum, plate 516.
      Scrophularia, plate 863.
      Coreopsis, plate 1283.
      Parthenium, plate 1402.
      All are Master set of color transparencies.
      No black and white negatives.
    - 23. Traite des arbres et arbustes. By Henri Louis Duhamel du Monceau
      Loaned by American Philosophical Society.
      Plate facing p. 230, Fagara.
      page 230.
      Plate facing Page 170, Cistus.
      Page 275.
    - 24. Vegetable productions...growing in this part of America. By Manesseh Cutler. In: Memoirs of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences
      page 396.
      page 397.
    - 25. Arbustum Americanum. By Humphry Marshall
      pp. 49-50 Reference to Franklin.
    - 26. Flora Caroliniana. By Thomas Walter
      Title page No negatives found.
      pp. 118-119.
    - 27. Index Flora Lancastriensis. By G.H.E. Muhlenberg
      Loaned by New York Academy of Medicine and New York Botanical Garden First published as Transactions of the American Philosophical Society.
      Title page (1793 ed.).
      p. 157 (1793 ed.).
      p. 158 (1793 ed.).
      Title page (1799 ed.).
      p. 235 (1793 ed.).
    - 28. Catalogus plantarum Americae Septentrionalis... By G.H.E. Muhlenberg
      Loaned by New York Academy of Medicine and New York Botanical Garden.
    - 29. Travel through North and South Carolina. By William Bartram
      Pages 164, 165.
      Plate facing p. 476, Andromeda Pulverulenta.
    - 30. The road to Xanadu. By John L. Lowes
      Page 368.
    - 31. Drawings made by William Bartram for John Fothergill
      Preliminary color proofs from Meridan Gravure Company.
      pp. 21, 27 plate xi and xiv (color transparencies).
      p. 33 plate xvii.
      pp. 67, 75, 77 (n. 6, 12, 1).
      p. 106 last two pages of letter.
      p. 106 Franklinia (color transparency).
    - 32. Collection for an essay towards a materia medica. By Benjamin Barton
      Loaned by New York Academy of Medicine and New-York Botanical Garden.
    - 33. Elements of botany. By Benjamin Barton
    - 34. Account of the late Mr. John Bartram. In: The Philadelphia medical and physical journal. By William Bartram
      Loaned by Paul Cranefield.
      Opening page to articel.
    - 35. Flora Boreali-Americana. By Andre Michaux
      Loaned by New York. Botanical Garden.
    - 36. Histoire des chenes. By Andre Michaux
      Engracing p. 23.
    - 37. Original drawings for Michaua's Histoire des chenes. By Pierre Redoute
      Loaned by the Royal Botanic Garden.
      p. 2 letter from Boott 30 Oct. 1825.
      pp. 9-10 Title spread.
      p. 56 letter and notes.
      pp. 176 and 179 engraving and drawing.
      pp. 50-51 text.
      pp. 239, 241, 245, drawings.
      p. 180 letter to Boott.
      Set of negatives in Box 1 (lacking p. 51 text).
    - 38. Histoire des arbes forestiers. By Francois Andre Michaux
      Plate Ire, Juglans, Black walnut.
    - 39. The North American Sylva. By Francois Michaux
    - 40. Florula Bostoniensis. By Jacob Bigelow
      Loaned by New. York Botanical Garden and New York Academy of Medicine.
    - 41. American medical botany. By Jacob Bigelow
      Loaned by New York Botanical Garden and New York Academy of Medicine.
      Title page, v. 1.
      Plate XIII, Thalmia Latifolia.
    - 42. Flora of North America. By William Barton
      Plate I, Lysimachia Racemosa.
    - 43. Florae Philadelphicae Prodromus. By William Barton
      Page OPP. title page. Inscription by author to James Monroe, President of the United States.
    - 44. A manual of botany for the United States. By Amos Eaton
    - 45. The genera of North American plants. By Thomas Nuttall
      pp. 152-153, v. 1.
    - 46. The North American sylva. By Thomas Nuttall
      Title page. v. 4.
      Plate X, Alnus Marrtima, seaside alder.
    - 47. Florula Ludoviciana. By Constantine Rafinesque Leaned by New York Botanical Garden
    - 48. Neogenyton. By Constantine Rafinesque
      Loaned by Stechert Hafner.
    - 49. New flora and Botany of North America. By Constantine Rafinesque
      Title page (2 different editions; same year).
      Text: pp. 5-7.
      Total of 6 pages.
    - 50. Alsographia Americana. By Constantine Rafinesque
      pp. 44-45 text.
    - 51. Florula cestrica. By William Darlington leaned by New York Botanical Garden and New York Academy of Medicine
      Title page and facing page.
      Facing p. 56, Plate 3: Talinum teretifolium.
    - 52. Memorials of John Bartram and Humphry Marshall. By William Darlington
      Title page-2 page spread.
      p. 31 and facing p. 31.
      no negatives found.
    - 53. A flora of the Northern and Middle... United States. By John Torrey
      negative in Box 1.
    - 54. Compendium. By John Torrey
      2 page title page spread each page of above separately.
    - 55. Flora of North America. By John Torrey
      Loaned By New York Botanical Garden.
      Title page, v. 1, pt. l.
    - 56. A flora of the state of New York. By John Torrey
      Plate 82, v. 2 Gentiana.
    - 57. Florula Princetoniana. By John Torrey
      Torrey's signature.
      page numbered 1.
      page numbered 2.
    - 58. Elements of botany. By Asa Gray
      pp. 298-299.
    - 59. Manual of botany. By Asa Gray
      pp. 446-447 together.
      pp. 446, 447 separately.
    - 60. A flora of North America. BY Asa Gray
      Loaned by Mew York Academy of Medicine and New York Botanical Garden.
      Title page, v. 2, pt. 2.
    - 61. Class-book of botany. By Alphonso Wood
      Title page pp. 56-57.
      Set of negatives in Box 1 (pp. 56-57 together and separately).
    - 62. An illustrated flora of the Northern United States. By Britton and Brown Leaned by New York Botanical Garden
      Title page, v. 2.
      pp. 542-543.
      Set of negatives in Box 1 (pp. 542-543 together and separately).
    - 63. The wild flowers of America. By Goodale and Sprague
      Plate I, Wild Columbine.
      Negative in box 1.
    - 64. Wild flowers of America. By Goodale and Sprague (1882)
      Place XXXIII, Blood Root.
      Negative in Box 1, also negative of title page.
    - 65. Wild flowers of the United states. Vol. 1: the Northeastern States By Harold W. Rickett
      Title pages, v. 1, pt. 1 pp. 132-133.